When it comes to something
as life-and-death important
as what to feed ourselves
and our families,
we should rely not on
anecdotes, but on facts.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Have you ever heard of the
trendelenburg position?
Lying in this position at
a slight head down tilt
may actually help
you burn fat.
Here’s the first story.
When our blood volume drops,
our kidneys detect it
and angiotensin is released.
When our blood volume rises,
on the other hand,
our heart detects it and
releases a hormone called ANP
(atrial natriuretic peptide,
also known as ANF,
atrial natriuretic factor).
We used to think our heart
was just a pump,
but now we know
it's also a gland.
There are stretch receptors in
the first chamber of our heart,
and when extra blood pours into
the heart, ANP is released.
What does it do?
As the title of a review
in an obesity journal put it:
"Heart hormones
fueling a fire in fat."
If you drip ANP on human fat
and muscle tissue,
fat is rapidly released
and the muscle cells ramp up
their capacity to burn it.
Infuse ANP into people
and the rate at which fat
is mobilized and burned
can shoot up 15 percent.
You can take muscle biopsies
from people and show
how much better their muscles
get at burning fat
in the presence
of elevated ANP levels.
No surprise then,
that obese
and overweight individuals
tend to have
considerably lower levels
in their bloodstream.
So, the way
to a person's stomach
may be through their heart.
Why would this
stretch-sensitive heart hormone
tap into our fat stores?
Well, when does the heart
get stretched?
During intense
physical activity.
We used to think it was just
the adrenaline-type hormones
that are released
when you exercise
that mobilized fat
from our tissues,
but now we know
that ANP from our heart
plays a key role as well.
Inject people
with the amount of ANP
they'd normally get
in their system when exercising,
and their whole-body fat burning
goes up,
even if they're just sitting
on the couch.
How else
can we stretch our heart
that extra little bit
to release ANP?
By increasing our blood volume
by drinking extra water.
When you don't drink
for 12 hours straight,
your ANP levels in your blood
fall by about 25 percent,
but chug down
about four glasses of water
and your levels
can jump up by 50 percent
within 90 minutes.
Now that's too much
to drink at one time,
but it can offer a sense
of how much potential control
we have
over this fat-burning hormone.
How else
could we trick our body
into producing
this exercise hormone
without lacing up
our gym shoes?
If it's all about pooling
extra blood into our heart,
what about lying
with our head tilted down?
It sounds kind of funny,
but researchers took
the possibility seriously enough
to run the experiment.
They laid people down
at just a six-degree angle,
a slight tilt that's like
putting three or four bricks
under the posts
at the foot of your bed.
So, it's not like
you're hanging upside down.
They were almost flat
but at just enough of a slant
for gravity to draw extra blood
into their torso.
Within an hour,
their ANP levels doubled
and stayed up for the four hours
the experiment ran.
Okay, but did they
all of a sudden
start burning more fat?
Yes, the proportion of fat
they were burning as fuel
shot up by 40 percent,
and they were just lying down
the whole time.
So, what if you tried sleeping
with a slight head-down tilt
by putting a few bricks
under the posts
at the foot of your bed?
Would it cause you to burn
more fat while you slept?
I'll address the potential pros
and cons next.
I noted how lying
at a slight, six-degree,
head-down tilt for a few hours
can boost fat burning.
Now obviously you wouldn't want
to lie tilted back
if you had a heart condition,
such as
congestive heart failure.
As many as 8 to 12 cups
(1.90 to 2.90 L) of blood
may be displaced into the torso
from the extremities
at a tilt like that,
so you have to have
the cardiovascular fitness
to handle it.
Acid reflux
could also be a problem.
In fact, we typically tell
heartburn patients
to do the reverse,
put a few bricks
under the posts
at the head of their bed
to have gravity work
in their favor
to keep stomach acid
down where it belongs.
But for those
without medical problems,
is there a harm to lying
tilted back for a few hours?
Well, it could give you
a "space headache."
In movies, astronauts are shown
practicing underwater,
but the gold standard
for simulating
the physiological effects
of the weightlessness
of outer space is HDBR,
head-down bed rest.
On Earth, our blood tends
to collect in our legs,
so our body is designed
to force blood headward.
In outer space,
our body is still trying
to push our blood "up,"
so without Earth's gravity,
blood pushes upwards
to our head and chest,
just like it does
when we lie tilted back.
This realization
came from cosmonauts
returning from
the space station
feeling as though
they were slipping
towards the foot of the bed,
and only feeling "normal"
when they were tilted
six degrees back.
All of the extra blood
pooling in the head
is thought to contribute
to the headaches
reported by up to 70 percent
of astronauts
during space flights,
and a similar percentage
of individuals suffer headaches
from prolonged
head-down bed rest.
That's after days, though.
In preparation
for a mission to Mars,
space agencies put people
through head-down bed rest
for prolonged periods,
eating, bathing,
and toileting
all while lying in bed
tilted back
for literally months at a time.
Extended stretches
of head-down positioning
for weeks may impair
lung function,
brain function,
and immune function,
and cause a loss
of muscle mass.
On the last Apollo mission,
the astronauts lost
about five pounds (2.30 kg)
of fat over the 12-day trip,
but they also lost
about two pounds (0.90 kg)
of lean body mass.
Prolonged weightlessness
or bedrest,
regardless of tilt,
can result
in muscle and bone loss.
But just sleeping on a slant
by putting a few bricks
under the posts
at the foot of your bed
could potentially give you
a boost in fat metabolism
without
the long-term adverse effects.
If you want to try it,
a note of caution:
take it slow
when standing back up.
After just four hours
of a six-degree head-down tilt,
most people experience reduced
"orthostatic tolerance."
When anyone stands suddenly
after sitting or lying down
for a while,
you can get a "head rush,"
feel dizzy, faint,
or lightheaded
as the blood drains
from your brain
down into your legs before
your body can compensate.
This can be exacerbated
by lying
with your head tilted back,
so be careful,
get up gradually.
Drinking two cups (0.50 L)
of cold water
30 minutes before rising
may also help.
Do not try this at home
if you have any heart
or lung issues
or problems with your brain
(like head trauma)
or eyes (even a family history
of glaucoma disqualifies you).
Ask your physician
if they think it's safe
for you to sleep
in "mild Trendelenburg."
Friedrich Trendelenburg
was a pioneering surgeon
that popularized the use
of what was formerly referred to
as "head-down position"
for certain abdominal
and pelvic procedures.
Angling the operating table
back 15 to 30 degrees
pulls some abdominal organs
out of the way
to help declutter
the surgical field,
resulting in
what is now widely known
as the Trendelenburg position.
Steep Trendelenburg,
like 25-, 30-degree tilt,
has been associated with
transient visual problems,
thought due to the increase
in pressure within the eyeball.
Cautions have been issued
for those at risk for glaucoma
(a disease
of increased eye pressure)
to avoid "inversion" therapy,
where people hang upside down,
as well as yoga positions
like handstands,
which can have a similar effect.
Lying back
in mild Trendelenburg,
like around six degrees,
can cause a fleeting bump
in eye pressure
that appears to normalize
within a few hours,
but the pooling of blood
in the head
may reduce blood flow
to the retina
sufficient
to impair nerve impulses.
Similar effects have been noted
within the brain.
Intracranial pressure
also normalizes
after a few hours
at a six-degree head-down tilt,
but the overall blood flow
through the brain
does drop a bit.
This is why
you shouldn't try this
if you have eye
or brain pathology.
To my surprise,
sleeping in mild Trendelenburg
was actually put to the test
to prevent bone loss
in sedentary individuals.
Restrict people's activity
to walking less than two miles
(3.20 km) a day on average,
and within a year
they can lose as much
as 15 percent
of their bone mineral density.
What happened
to those randomized
to the same exercise restriction
but also combined with sleeping
at a two-degree head-down tilt
that was increased
by two degrees
about every two months
so they ended up sleeping
at a 14-degree slant
(or whatever angle
they felt comfortable with)
by the end of the year?
Not only did it completely block
the bone loss,
they built more bone.
Despite
the movement restriction,
they ended up
with about 12 percent greater
bone mineral density
than when they started.
Note that
this bone-building effect
was only apparent
in sedentary individuals.
Another group randomized
to the same mild Trendelenburg,
but assigned to run
an average of five or six miles
(8 or 9.5 km) a day
just maintained
their same skeletal integrity.
The study was repeated,
and the same remarkable effects
were found.
There is something about the
"periodic fluid redistribution"
that comes with sleeping
tilted back at night
that actively builds
both bone density and volume
after the day-long
stagnant pooling of blood
in the legs
of sedentary individuals.
The research team claims
that this is just the beginning
to the benefits,
citing "unpublished studies"
asserting a near panacea
of perks
to sleeping in Trendelenburg.
I can't be too critical
of this apparent dodge
when I can't point
to a single study
supporting my supposition that
it will help with weight loss.
As far as I can tell,
it's never been tried
or even proposed.
What I can promise
is that any researchers
who take on the mantle
of putting it to the test
will definitely have
their study featured
in a video on
NutritionFacts.org.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
If you see any graphs, charts,
graphics, images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My latest major book,
“How Not to Age” is out.
Check it out from your
local public library.
Of course, all the proceeds
I receive of the sales
of all my books
go to charity.
I actually just came out
with another small book:
an easy 100-page read on
Ozempic and other GLP-1 drugs.
Go to NutritionFacts.org
and click on “Books”
to see where you can get an e-book,
audiobook, or paperback of it.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There are no ads,
no corporate sponsorships,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.